one so welcome everyone
to a another q a on the awakening
from the meaning crisis discord our
guest today is
rafe kelly and uh he has been the
subject of a couple voices with vervecki
and has talked with john as well on his
channel
now as i was looking into ray from
preparation for this
i basically came to the conclusion that
rafe kelly
is a real life batman and i'm not
exaggerating on that he started training
in martial arts at age six
and he studied tang sudo aikido kung fu
kickboxing bjj muay thai
caporia and sistema at eight
he met his mentor who i imagine as
liam neeson as rajal ghoul in batman
begins
who trained rafe in movement rough
housing with him daily
allowing him to roam the woods for hours
each day introduced him to texts like
the iliad in the odyssey
he discovered a love of anthropology and
evolutionary
biology which he studied later in
college at 15 he began
studying gymnastics and at 23 discovered
pork
parkour and if you haven't watched the
video of rafe that i posted in the
announcements
you really need to watch it it's it's
quite incredible plus
his channel is filled with amazing
videos to watch
the rape went on to co-found parkour
visions where he was the head instructor
and then developed the idea for evolve
more play of
sorry evolve move play and he's been
traveling the world teaching studying
and immersing himself in movement and
research
so like i said he's got he's got the
training
philosophy martial arts he's basically
he's basically he's basically batman uh
so thank you ray for being here
yeah thanks for having me so so
uh usually just start off asking a
couple introductory questions
so you're the founder of evolve move
play can you tell us what that is
yeah i do want to i just i wanted to say
something about my mentor because it
made me laugh
um you you you um
imagine him in your head as razal ghul
uh which is really funny because he was
a uh
he was a gay man who was a hairdresser
um and he was from
uh is from uh the appalachian region so
he was
from the the corner where north carolina
west virginia
and virginia all meet had a virginian
accent it was a very slender
of uh uh he actually looked like
it looked like um the very anglo
um anglo versions of jesus
right you know that that slender blonde
jesus that you see in all the
pictures being hanged looked like that
but with worse teeth and more english
i just thought that was funny so not not
aroused that goal but he brought
out ghoul perhaps
so yeah if all moved play what was the
question about evolving
play well just tell us about it what
what is it and
uh yeah tell us tell us all about it
yeah so the basic idea of evolving play
is that
human beings can evolve to be sedentary
one of the fundamental problems that we
have in the current world
is lack of movement um but that we
evolved
to learn and acquire movement to
experience movement
plot through play animals that have
uh that have almost all animals have to
move in order to
survive right uh actually they acquire a
lot of their movement skill through play
as juveniles
the more more kind of really complex an
animal is actually the more it plays
human beings play more than any other
animals somehow our culture
has has forgotten that and has started
to view play as very
endless and whimsical and as not part of
the important
aspects of development something that we
need to recover
was the idea behind the name um it's
evolved quite a bit since i
originated it so i had been doing
parkour
so i started involvement play in 2013.
doing
parkour at that since 2005 so eight
years
even a year into my parkour training i
had uh discovered
an older french method called nato
natural which included not just
running jumping vaulting etc but also
included
swimming um lifting caring
throwing and self-defense i was
interested right away
in bringing all these things together in
one method
um the gymnastics background martial
arts background and i wanted to kind of
um have a method that incorporated all
of that
so i actually started developing the
antecedents involved move play back in
2006 2007
um but i was working with with what
became
movement and the founder of what became
move now i didn't feel that that
project was quite going where i wanted i
felt like part of it was there was no
fun art in what what we created that
uh either of us had mastery of so i
decided that parkour was where i was
going to focus and
and reach a level of mastery that could
give me an insight into
that process that i could carry into a
broader discipline so i stuck with
parkour until 2013
um and then i and then by that time i
run into all the play research and i had
brought that play orientation to it and
i'd run into ido portal and the ideas
around movement
brought that into it and so i was
teaching
and and doing all this stuff with the
bald move play
and i i noticed this interesting trend
which was that
i was very scientifically minded and i
did a lot of
primary research on mechanics and
strength conditioning on how people you
know evolutionary theory
and i would share stuff about that so
people could understand
better how to move people appreciated
that about me the education that i
brought
i noticed that as i wove my own personal
life
story into my teachings that had a much
bigger impact on me
um so i i started to see this power of
storytelling
and ask myself what's going on there how
do i understand that better
and um
i i can't remember actually if it was a
friend of mine or if it was just
youtube but one way or another in
october of 2016 like i suspect many of
you in the room
um i was exposed to jordan peterson
um through his interview on the joe
rogan podcast
and i was interested in the political
aspect of what he was talking about but
as he got into
maps of meaning and his archetypes i was
when
eyes really lit up and i got very
interested
so it just happens because i teach
primarily outdoors that i don't
really teach any that i haven't
traditionally taught any seminars
between
november and um march
from november to march instead of
listening to
um instead of listening to podcasts
about strength conditioning and reading
things about strength conditioning i
consumed
everything that jordan peterson uh had
put out that i could i
i was by by
march when i taught my first summer i
think i'd listen to 160 hours of just
uh personality and maps and meaning
lectures um
completely when i went to t and i kept
my asking myself this question like
why am i obsessed with this guy's work
what does it have to do with my work
um and i went out to teach
march and all of a sudden i saw that
this evolutionary frame
i was applying to movement and how
movement could impact you as a human
being
actually very much aligned with this
sort of evolutionary frame
that peterson was looking at human
behavior in general from
you can map them very close to each
other that was very
interesting because as interesting as it
wasn't until i was actually
teaching a workshop i would start
talking about something
that would trigger something i
remembered from having
listened to peterson and i would see the
connection between became clear
why it was so interesting to me the act
actually um i i
dug very deep into his work and into the
question of the meaning
meaning and um and i that i ended up
getting
uh it was people in the embodiment
community
and started to had have independently
been really
uh running into a lot of people in the
world of nature connection which is
obviously related to
the natural parkour element of what i do
and uh and and so these things were
coming together
and then i found verveicky's work and
started talking fakie and his idea of
the ecology of practices really hit home
for me and described what i kind of
organically grown through
my workshops and research so we've come
to think of what we do
as essentially a system
of self-transformation right or an
ecology of practices where we're putting
an ecology of practices that afford
transformation jerome potential for
greatness
and service of the good and
you do that with with what we think of
as the primary connections that people
need which are connection to their body
and movement
action to um community connection to the
natural environment of connection to
money
there's four pillars in what we do
and
our idea of what the greatness is is we
need to
facilitate the capacity to see clearly
the world okay
as it is which is kind of the archetype
of horus
and we need to be able to have to
articulate
what we see and develop knowledge out of
it which is
we use socrates as our archetype for
that we need to be able to
develop have to cultivate in ourselves
with strength physically and emotionally
to utilize that knowledge we don't want
to be
she's intellectual with a giant ear and
a shrunken natural body
want to actually embody these things um
and
we need strength we need emotional
courage to do that and so for us
strength is
is is the you know the archetype is uh
or hercules and the emotional archetype
is against socrates or the buddha
and then um then you need skillfulness
we we love that the celtic god luke as a
representation of skillfulness
have skills to apply to solving these
problems all of that helps you solve
that anomaly that can
happen at any time in your life that
helps you
engage in that that sense of
transcendence and meaning in your life
so
we gain meaning from uh from
being connected to things that give
meaning to life and we
gain meaning through oriented in a
process of becoming
uh the most heroic version of ourselves
so that's quite a long answer so i hope
it was interesting
oh yes that that was great that's
fascinating now now
you're i mean your your work is obvious
obviously very physical and it demands
sort of peak physical fitness and now
not everybody is not everybody is
is in peak physical fitness so
what do you say to the people who who
aren't ready to
jump through trees and you know
use the the world as their jungle gym
how would you apply how would
how could they apply what your methods
and what you've done
without having a method is actually
designed for
all levels for all physical levels the
expression of it that you see
within me um is you know
someone perhaps at the peak of physical
ability
but it doesn't matter so much right
so i can jump between two tree branches
say 30 feet off the ground
um for me that's a useful thing because
i've conditioned myself in many ways and
it
provides an edge i can sharpen myself on
um but as far as its passage to
transform me it's
no more profound um at least not in the
fundamental way somebody who's totally
unfit
doing their first jump at ground level
that
that that moment of the jump is
formative to them
that's what we're aimed at is the
transformation of the character
through the the means of the and
that's the case you know it's not so
much about
much you can accomplish that's you know
we love that and we care about it but
ultimately the the value of the journey
isn't measured in the heights of the
physical achievements
dude and how much change you can make or
profoundly changes
that individual's character so our
students range in
age from three years old to 73 years old
and we've had people who are um
extremely overweight people who have not
trained
uh you know in 20 years 30 years or 40
years
actually one of our regular students in
our classes is
recovering from a traumatic brain injury
so you know he's gone from
really being able to lift up his left
leg to being able to do step vaults and
crawl under branches and little bits of
climbing
so it's it's absolutely for everybody
for me it doesn't matter
where you start from not addressing the
body
as part of your self-transformation
practice
um you're not a dr you're
missing something of extraordinary
importance here you
are a body and you can't escape it
if you don't have that integrated into
your self-transformation practice
um it can never be what it could be
that's a great answer yeah and certainly
we can take
we could we can all take that and john's
just started
in this meditation class for example
teaching somewhere the bodywork
uh for us so everyone should should
check that out
uh he was doing some tai chi like uh
movements uh in
in this week's lesson so
so there's a there's a bridge there um
so so great i'd like to thank you so
much for that i'd like to to open up for
questions now
i think what we started doing yesterday
with john
was to have people queue up their
questions
you don't have to write out the full
question but maybe if you're interested
in a question
um put it in the event listening party
chat and
if you don't have a mic and would like
me to
read it out or or for whatever reason
want me to re read it out just
let me know so i think strewn strawn has
the
uh his first stop uh so
go ahead uh strong uh hi rafe
uh mr amy i can right yeah so
um i noticed that you brought up two
things uh in your conversations with uh
john reiki the one was the issue of
being and becoming
and the other was pragmatic value versus
objective truth
and i was wondering if you connect those
dots at all and if you do then how
i missed about half of that strong
um okay so you brought up two things
uh with to john viveki being and
becoming
and then objective value oh sorry
objective truth versus pragmatic value
and i was wondering if you connect those
dots at all and if you do then how
i haven't thought about the relationship
between the idea of
of being orientation and becoming
orientation
and how that relates to um
to a objective worldview versus a
pragmatic worldview
okay well um thanks thanks for your
question though
think about it you have any uh do you
have any ideas about that
um yeah well several but um i was
yeah i don't know it's a bit outside the
end bit of a quick q and a question so
if you really want me to get into it
then i could get into contact with you
somehow but uh
yes i can email you over here okay right
thanks john so
skyler huckleberry go ahead
hello um my question is
sort of about uh parkour and
circumambulation and cultural landmarks
or national monuments
i was wondering if you've ever
considered
having a course that truly moves all the
way around
a central object and
i know that afterwards you often go into
campfires or other
ways of dialoguing about the experience
and i'm just wondering how those can be
brought at a local level
i live in beautiful arizona i can think
of places
that i could take you in all the way
around a mountain
and then we could go on top of that
mountain and talk about
going all the way around that mountain
things like that so
you're you're interested in in the idea
of how
kind of having a completed journey um
would provide a a a capacity for insight
generation
having yeah that's it uh
circumambulation peterson has talked
about the church where a maze
you have to go through all quadrants
before you're allowed into the center of
it
so you kind of walk the journey for
everyone and it allows you to
see it from any angles many perspectives
interesting i mean it's not something
that we do within
parkour right parkour tends to be about
finding
um very kind of resource dense
areas that offer a lot of um
a lot of potential to explore movement
so
um i like to think about parkour
as being kind of a terrain based sport
in the same way that
mountain biking and um
you know downhill skiing freestyle
skiing surfing etc
are it's about finding these areas that
offer lots of potential for women
and then exploring them
starting my daughter stacking in the
background um
so um we do within my work do some
longer movements like at our big
retreat we do a big journey around
um an alpine area
do what's called the chain lakes trail
all the way around it
but i've never specifically tried to
think about that from a ritual stamp
thing that i've been with a lot recently
is just starting to think about in my
work is the role of ritual
if you guys have already uh i imagine
some of you have read maps of meaning
and they have that
um he has that description of the
development
of knowledge right we move from
exploratory behavior
to imitation of that exploratory
behavior
play to um ritual
and from ritual to narrative and drama
or drama and narrative literature and
only later into philosophy and very late
into something like science
and i notice a commonality with that in
the way that we
essentially how movement behavior is
generated
you can look at a group of people who
are just starting to learn parkour and
they'll go to an area
they will start exploring that area
and then over time they'll start to
notice some kind of
movement sequence or movement it's
particularly intriguing and then they'll
repeat that movement often
one person will find a movement and
other people will then adopt the
movement that they're working on
once that movement is starting to get
well controlled
you'll see is people start adding
variation to it a lot of what play is is
essentially taking a behavior that is uh
that has shown that it's adaptive and
adding variations to it because it
builds your behavior flexibility
in some sense all of parkour is kind of
play because you're you're doing that
but you can see even within it there's
this it's the same sequence
um now at our big retreats we
we do this climb through a waterfall and
it's at the end of the third or fourth
day it's kind of the peak
of the event and we you know we
run down this creek for about two hours
to get to this
waterfall and usually people have been
moving that day for about
seven or eight hours by the time we get
to the waterfall
and they have to climb through this
waterfall and
[Music]
it's a tunnel and a rock it's a chimney
basically that you're stemming up
through as the water is pouring down on
your head
and there's really no way to completely
prepare someone for getting
in there because you've never
experienced anything like it
um and there's no way to describe it and
i can't really take you in there and do
it with you you have to go through it
so i think of that as kind of the
initiation ritual that we use
um and so we welcome everybody and it's
kind of like being reborn through the
earth
and so i think about this idea of that
as
as a ritual but i think that
lately i've been thinking about the idea
that like
ritual there that there's ways of
manipulating
the the rituals to make them more
powerful
um and we're kind of a discovering
ritual within our practice
but we don't necessarily have the same
technology that um that traditional
religions have or shamanic
shamanic traditions have and so i'm very
interested in like
i've thought about the idea of fasting
for 24 hours and then
going to do this ritual um i'm doing
some very very intense physical stuff to
to put myself into an altered state and
then going through it
and then using that as a as a as an
insight
generation tool i don't know if that is
precisely along the same lines of what
you're asking about
um that's kind of
where we're thinking about about uh
about ritual coming into our practice
but i'd just like to pick up on that for
a second so so
i don't know how much you you've spent
looking at john's idea of the religion
that's
not a religion i've thought that
you know he talks a lot about the
importance of ritual and rituals that
can be borrowed from other traditions
but
you know it seems to me that for the
religion that's not a religion to really
take off
it needs to have its own rituals you
know new rituals that have been designed
specifically for it you know in the
modern day
do you have any thoughts on that about
the development of new rituals and
and i should ask what are your thoughts
on the religion yeah
sorry sir john and i just recorded
another conversation i reached out to
him
to talk about a set of insights that i'd
had
during my sit spot practice um kind of
combining ideas from
peterson with david abrams who's a
ecology
uh philosopher um who wrote a book
called the spell of the sensuous and
he's kind of in the tradition of martial
ponti from the
um phenomenology tradition and and then
reading c.s lewis to my kids
all this came together and at the end of
my conversation with
with john um he said to me
you know what you've done right and i
was like what he said
you've created a church and
i
it's a hard one for me i mean there's a
truth to it and there's a
seems to me as we're watching the
craziness that's unfolding across
america right now that
the old idea you
you really can't get rid of religion in
people you can only
uh replace religion with some other
religion and if you do it carelessly if
you just try to tear it out a lot of
times what replaces it
um is much less sophisticated and
delivers a lot less value
i'm i'm very interested in that idea and
you know i i listen to ja
to paul vander clay and jonathan pedro
some of the folks who are arguing for
um like a full recommitment to
christianity
um and when honestly when peterson put
out the the biblical series i told my
wife like
you know when i get done watching this i
might be a christian
i haven't become
i'm i just don't have the felt
sense that there is a uh
something outside of nature two worlds
mythology
is unintuitive to me
um and uh
it feels like it to to adopt the two
worlds mythology
requires me to fudge my epistemology
in a way that doesn't feel correct to me
so in the event i guess i'm very much in
john's camp of we need religio
we need to somehow divorce it from
dogma and
i'm not 100 sure how to do that
what i notice is that within some of
these practices
it seems like there are there's there's
religious or spiritual dimensions that
are emerging
it's very interesting to me you know
perhaps this is my bias
perhaps i'm seeing how when you get a
new car you see that car everywhere
maybe because i've looked at all this
stuff i see this in all sorts of people
who are
doing parkour all of a sudden it's like
lots of people within the parkour
community got interested in jordan
peterson
you know people are reading the hero's
journey people are rediscovering
christianity
or going into taoism or going into
buddhism it's like there's an incipit
spirituality i think there's a kind of
incipient spirituality
spiritual element to almost every
sport that is truly a flow sport that
really gives you deep access to flow
state i think perhaps the
mental states that are associated with
spiritual and religious experiences of
very close
those states so there's something
that's that's already happening there
and then the question is
uh this is something that we need
they're a way to leverage that
to to build those pieces that are
missing
i've been to christian services and i've
been through the rituals
and for me they were uh
felt very empty and dead
and yet seeing people who have profound
experiences from them
i feel like i'm seeing those same types
of experiences
through some of these movement
events um and other events like them
so i i think the role of ritual is is
something
that's very interesting and it's also
something that i don't feel like i have
fully grocked yet
right and that's a
that's understandable uh you know
rituals evolved over
over many many years and we're talking
about creating them
you know on purpose just you know from
scratch
i mean that's a lot of what we're doing
around here is talking about the
religion that's not a religion and
what it could look like you know there's
a lot of brainstorming going on right
now
yeah yeah my
bias on that i guess is
it seems to me as inheritors of the west
that a lot of the grammar that is going
to be
easiest for us to
to kind of function on
is going to come from a christian
framework actually i honestly believe
that
i'm not 100 certain about this because i
don't know i've been very influenced by
peterson and i haven't
spent the same amount of time studying
taoism or buddhism
or some of these other traditions it
seems to me that what verveiki has
has articulated and what piercing have
articulated about
the kind of core idea of christianity
within
the pursuit of the logos and in treating
the world
with agape um are kind of
the the best spiritual truths around
which you can orient yourself that's
what
you know when i talked about the idea of
building your capacity for greatness in
service of the good
that's what i meant um
we wrote out this this whole roadmap
to do uh
what we were trying to create with the
bald move play and we talked about this
idea we need to create
with vision capacity to articulate we
need to create people who are
strong physically and emotionally we
need to create people who have skills
that they can apply to solving problems
um what i realized as i was looking at
that was that
i could describe someone who is great
and evil
as well as if you describe someone who
is great and good
that if you are pursuing something like
that um
without looking beyond it towards the
good
um don't know what you're you're
empowering in some sense
so for me the good has to be in some
sense that
uh capacity for agape and
the funny thing about that is that hey
my practice of building agape in myself
is buddhist right i use meta meditation
which is part of the ecology of
practices that
john uses it was taught to me my friend
mark walsh
all right so one second audrey can you
not be in here please sorry we're
getting interrupted by children
that's all right not a problem
the highest the highest good is is that
agape principle i use buddhism
i think that the story of christ
archetypally is the most powerful
expression of that that i've ever
encountered
um and
i think in taoism and buddhism there's
an extraordinary
amount of wealth of wisdom that is
actually very
alignable with that basic region
but where i where i get stuck is i
cannot accept
epistemologically commitment to the
resurrection
yeah thank you that's a great answer and
children
uh running back and forth yeah
that it's quite all right so nick's got
a question
hey ray uh yeah my name's nick
um i was i was this is a bit lighter of
a question but
i was wondering if you ever came across
the tricking community
yes nice
uh i don't know that much about tricking
um you know obviously
obviously lots of parkour athletes
adopted pre-runners have adopted tricks
from the tricking community
right so we've learned lots of tricks
like one of my
core techniques that i'm working on
right now that i just sort of started to
be able to land consistently as a
corkscrew
which is really nice um
yeah i saw you do a webster in the uh
the little video that
uh someone posted in our our chat and
it got me thinking um
yeah that's that's that's that's great i
know there's a lot of crossover between
the communities and was curious
um interestingly my um
the guy who i kind of my my core
business partner
you know my number one tenant in what
i'm doing
uh he he he's uh
has a strong tricking background he's
kind of a free runner who likes lots of
tricking and he's also
a um a devout christian so it's kind of
an interesting intention for us because
i'm a very like traditionally pure
parkour guy and an atheist and he's a
christian so yeah there was
there was all that drama way back in the
day uh
when the two communities started really
interacting with each other
um i guess the other question i had is
somewhat related to that and that's
um you know i was doing this uh tricking
as a as a teenager
and uh you know i'm 30 now
and i still keep up the basics but um
you know i don't have a whole lot of
cartilage left in my knees to work with
uh and so i was wondering as someone
who's done these practices
for a long time um how
you have learned how to offset
some of the damage that one can take
keeping up a regular practice of a more
extreme sport
yeah oh you know this is a story i tell
a lot but
uh i kind of adopted the
the framework of professional athletics
give a sense of meaning and purpose to
my parkour and the initial um
excitement of it isn't working for me
anymore
and you know i started i
started some of the first competitive
parkour
events in north america and in the world
really
and i uh i was competing in them at the
same time that i was running them
i was like dieting down to get lean
enough to to to be like an optimal body
weight because i'm a very
guy naturally um you know most parkour
athletes are between like 140
and maybe 180 pounds and i'm naturally
like over 200.
so i wanted to get really light and the
panic attack
my first competition um and there was a
few other things going on in my life but
over the course of 18 months i
had uh subluxated my cuboid bone
toward ligaments in both my feet two
back spasms
tore an old rotator cuff injury
had an ac separation uh echo
microclavicular separation
and um and my achilles tendon
and then a little like a high ankle
sprain and
um you know that up
then that all happened between like i
guess 27
30 uh so two between 2010 and
um 2012. i i healed up and was doing
pretty good
i keep so i came back from my achilles
tendon pair
and nine months later i was on the show
american ninja warrior
and i i just missed qualifying to go to
japan that was the last
year that they took athletes from the
american show and something in japan
um so i was really happy about that i
beat all my
local friends in the in the competition
um i have tim sheef
um pretty pretty stoked about that and
then i went to the apex
edition competitions and so i did well
but then i kind of lost my motivation
for it and i was coming back
um pete 2013 at the
north american park championships and i
was training with a student of mine
who'd become very successful
at that and the week before
it all went down i retored my rotator
cuff again
and i went and uh
went and did the qualifying competition
and i finished
third in the qualifying competition and
so i qualified in to compete
but the only way for me to make it
through the first course would have
required me to do a
16-foot running jump to catch with my
hands
i knew my shoulder would give out i
stopped
and after after that i basically
um looked in the mirror and said you
know like you can keep taping yourself
together
for a couple more years and try to
really push your competitions
you probably take injuries that will
limit you
the rest of your life and being able to
do this thing love
or you can shift your focus towards how
can i have a sustainability focus
on these practices and so
i had a few injuries in the last
seven years nothing on the severity of
what i've experienced then
and i've gotten really good at
learning to deal with and overcome the
little aches and pains that you get and
to build up the system
i mean the basic thing to remember about
physical practices is that
same things that injure you are the
things that make you strong
it's all about the dose if you're if
you're
you're trying to peak really hard right
now
it's very possible that you're doing
yourself damage long term
however you can do the exact same things
and with just a little bit different
mindset you can actually be building a
buffer that will make you more and more
injury proof as you go forward
we have a whole aspect of what we do
called body integrity practices which is
about looking at
specific demands of whatever we most
like to do
and saying how can we build up the
buffers in our body
so that we um we're not injury also we
have to look at
the lifestyle factors just the
hour and a half of tricking that you do
that hurts you it's the 20 hours of
sitting a day that you
hurt you um
and so you can't necessarily you know
maybe when you're
18 and you're not very and you don't
have a full-time job
you know uh afford to go out to train
just throw out a throw down and not take
care of all of the
bad stuff that's built up but when you
are stressed out and you've been working
60 hours a week sitting on a computer
you try to just go through your tricks
you're going to hurt yourself
so you need to start to understand not
only
uh the sport can hurt you and how to
buffer yourself from that
how your lifestyle is hurting you how to
overcome that
uh that's i have a very long answer to
that question
um but that's actually a huge aspect of
what we do we have four pillars
in our body aspect of our practice body
integrity
body to environment and object and body
to body practices
and we don't you won't you don't see
that in like the video that was shared
it's a huge aspect what we do because
i'm 38 years old
many ways i'm performing the best that
i've ever performed and there's very few
other people
um in the sport who are doing something
right
right yeah that was great thank you for
answering and
that's definitely a great point but it's
a lot less of the uh
immediate activity and and uh you know
how the rest of your life is uh
lending itself to that activity or not
okay guys
thank you welcome i have to highlight
this so
sorry about the the kid thing um but
this is really funny
the kids are are running around stomping
on the roof right now
which normally would be okay because
like i've they they're allowed to be
climbers and to do crazy
stuff that's part of our lifestyle but
it's
it's ironic their heroic quests are uh
interrupting our conversations at the
moment my poor wife is going crazy
she's on a call i'm on a call and the
kids are
been kicked outside so that they don't
give us crazy
and their answer to that was to climb on
the roof and start jumping
that's incredible my kids would be very
very jealous
sherry jerry's up next
hi rave um i have a question about mind
body um
i've been really can you hear me okay i
can hear you
okay i've been really um curious about
um why we have a body
that might seem like a strange question
or a strange
observation but um i'm a christian
and i'm reading um i'm reading
the early church fathers and they really
tackle
this idea of body and mind
quite quite often so i just wanted to
read you
a quote um just to put it in into
context
so this is from and i'm not exactly sure
when he wrote this
second century or something it is one
thing to see
and another to know to see and to be
seen
is a property of bodies to know
and be known is an attribute of
intellectual being
whatever therefore is a property of
bodies
and he's just going to get into a little
bit of um christian
um you go back for a second cause you
you you broke
uh your your your voice broke for a
second for me there i didn't hear you
said um see and be seen and then you
stopped
okay it is it is one thing to see
and another to know to see and to be
seen
is a property of bodies to know
and to be known an attribute of
intellectual being
so then he talks about the relationship
between the father and the son
and he says whatever therefore is a
property of bodies
cannot be predicated either of the
father or of the son
but what belongs to the nature of deity
is common to the father
and the son finally even he himself
in the gospel did not say that no one
has
seen the father save the son nor anyone
the son
save the father but his words are
no one knows the son save the father nor
anyone
the father save the son by which it is
clearly shown
that whatever among bodily natures is
called seeing and be
seen being seen is termed
between the father and the son and
knowing and being
known by the means of power of knowledge
not by the frailness of the sense of
sight
okay so without getting all caught up in
the weeds
of christian doctrine my question
is
whether you're a christian or a buddhist
you're you're moving towards
transcendence right you're moving
towards
um something above you and that
connection is made by the mind
what is the purpose of the body
in that relationship because it has a
purpose
so what what exactly is the purpose of
the body
in a transcendent relationship
um you did break up again for a little
bit uh
so where were we uh
without getting caught up in
in the weeds yeah without getting caught
up in the weeds i think
you broke down there okay
so my my question is
can you hear me okay uh yeah
yeah i can now we'll see how long it
lasts
okay sorry about that um my question is
if you are pursuing transcendence
whether you're a christian or a buddhist
what is the role of the body because i
i i gather that
transcending is is is kind of something
that is
exclusive to the intellect to the mind
but i understand that the body plays a
role in that so my question is what is
that
role that the body is playing
yeah it's an interesting question and
you know
might be answered very differently from
detectives the thing that occurs to me
is i always root things in an
evolutionary perspective
um first question to me is not what is
the purpose of the body but what is the
purpose
evolutionary sorry you just you just
broke up there a bit rafe can you just
repeat that
um i said what is the purpose of the
body
uh in a kind of spiritual context um is
the question
and the first thing that occurs to me is
actually to
reverse the question what is the purpose
of the mind
because i always tend to first root
things
in evolutionary predictive um
as uh jordan peterson talks about it's
kind of the outermost frame that you
can't get beyond
being with and what we know
from uh evolutionary perspective is that
the mind evolves
to control a body that it is
as the body becomes more complex and the
need of more control the nervous system
becomes more complex so
when we look at uh there's an animal
called a c
squirt for instance and c squirts have
two
phases to their life one phase in which
they're mobile and one in which they
plant themselves
and basically sit the barnacle
what's interesting about that is that
during the mobile phase of their life
they have
a fairly extensive nervous system once
they become sedentary once they
they they settle into their
adult form they actually digest their
own brain
nervous system no longer functional from
a nervous system
the the brain first evolves control
movement
my argument is always that we cannot
optimize the function
of brain um
or the
mind the heart the emotions the nervous
system
um without putting it in the body and
this is something that vervekey talks
about
quite a lot this is foreign cognitive
science
mission is inherently embodied
embedded extended and enacted
let's come out of cybernetic theory the
recognition that if you try to
design something that has the capacity
of perception
it's actually very hard to get it to
perceive the way that we perceive unless
you give it
the capacity for a motor action that
maps the type of motor actions that we
do
so perception and action are in some
sense
mutually affording have to have both
and this is a critique of christianity
that comes out of nietzsche right that
have
have essentially sacrificed the world
we've sacrificed the body
we what i can tell you from my personal
experience
is that in the pursuit of
physical endeavors i have experienced
great deals of
personal training that's kind of
where i think my role in this whole
conversation
is i i as as a
member of the conversation on meaning
with verveiki and peterson and all these
people
what's unique about my perspective is
that i have
gone deeper into physical practice and
almost everybody else and i can then
take those insights in that
philosophical philosophy
that is being shared by these people and
i can give it a grounding
physical practice so
i think that uh
we have bodies for a reason right um if
we think about this spiritually
uh we could say that for some reason
we're here and we have experiences
that the body is inextricable for those
experiences
as for reiki points out we can't even
think
about without experiencing
it's without being physical we've got a
lot of feedback all of a sudden
um i'm reading a beautiful book that you
might want to pick up called the spell
of the sensuous by david abrams who i
mentioned earlier
picks up a lot of the same themes that
verviki talks about which is that
essentially like
when you think you are
when you engage in your capacity for a
rational intelligent
knowing words
what they are is the representation of
the motor actions of forming
speech in your mouth rooted in the sense
right yep see something is to be rooted
in the sense of sight
some things to be rooted in the sense of
feeling so
i i don't have a sense of a
of a other world that this is in service
to
even if you do you might ask
is there not a reason we are here
that we have been given a type of mind
is inextricably linked to a body
that what we are neither
is not there is no cogitator you have to
have both
to be a full being being is embedded in
body
and it's actually something my friend
andrew talks
about who is uh like i said a devout
christian
but he's very he he points very strongly
to the idea that
when christ talks about uh
the you know the saving of everyone and
the kingdom of heaven
everyone who who died is going to come
bodily back into existence that the idea
of the complete separation of soul
body something that he sees is
non-biblical
so that's getting into weeds of
christianity that are way beyond
pay grade perhaps something
okay thank you very much rave well i i
just want to say that was an incredible
answer
so thank you very much for that next up
is tyler
hey reef um i'm also 38
and i uh i like nick
very much enjoyed a similar style of
running amok and doing as many twirls
and twists and flips as i could at a
younger age but
it's not necessarily the degradation of
the body from that work but i also have
an autoimmune condition that has
really limited mobility in many ways um
are you aware of any sets of techniques
or practices or do you guys focus on any
of that in
your work that can uh
provide some support for those who are
limited in mobility in that way
and also i took just one second
cut out at basically you told me that
you were whether you had an autoimmune
condition
no problem this is uh discord
uh we so yeah um with autoimmune
condition are you aware of any
sets of techniques or practices that
something that you guys focus on
perhaps that can support individuals who
have this limited mobility not just uh
in in relation to age but um
like my hands for instance are
particularly weak in grip strength
but my legs may be fine for running and
and jumping
um yeah so that and also i looked at the
video of you running around in the woods
it was fantastic and those trees are
absolutely
perfect do you think that we should
build our world in such a way that
that our ordinary spaces have these
perfectly configured mobility areas
or or is it is it more fun to go out
into the world and try to
find spots and use them as they are
okay well let's start with uh the
uh autoimmune thing and then we'll go
into the
we should build our world and are the
the resources
the um thing is i actually have an
immune condition myself or a couple i
have ibs
irritable bowel disease um and i have
vitiligo
since i was and i i get quite sore from
training more so than most of my
training partners and i believe it's
because i have a heightened inflammatory
response to
i have found that meditation does help i
can help my body
release that um at uh
that inflammation by meditating on it
i had a really profound experience with
this where
um it was suffering very badly from
bs symptoms um it was making it hard for
me to sleep it was making
me like be focused at work i had brain
all the time
um and had worked with a doctor
who was helping me um giving me lots of
supplements and it kind of helped but
i just want to live my life
like 40 different supplements at a time
and you know they ran out and i was in
europe and
i came back and i was really suffering
and i had run into the work of my friend
dave wardman who does something called
physical outcome he talked about we
talked about this idea of
interception the idea that you can feel
what's going on inside you
in the traditional chinese um island
and taoist culture there's this idea
that you could you could
learn to essentially auto regulate your
organ system you could learn to
not auto regulate but to consciously
regulate your immune
your organ systems you strong enough
meditator
i decided one day to sit down and
meditate and i did
a concentration meditation for probably
10 minutes
i did a body and i used that body scan
meditation to go into
and so basically i felt my breath and my
lungs
repeatedly then i tried to take that
into feeling my heart
and trying to feel different parts of
the heartbeat
and even trying to slow the heartbeat
down by holding the pause longer
i have achieved that sometimes it's
pretty weird um
and then i went from the heartbeat down
into
the stomach right and try to feel the
blood around the stomach then down into
the small intestine
large intestine in the colon i meditated
on essentially giving
the peristalsis of my gut to slow down
i meditated on this kind of cooling yin
energy
and uh this is a little bit personal but
i was having between 12 to 16 bowel
minutes a day
um the time leading up to that and that
day it was down to six and after that it
was down to
pretty much went forward um that was
very
powerful for me um also found the
carnivore diet is very powerful for
uh for autoimmunes um
i i was quite skeptical when peterson
peterson saying it i had friends who did
it give it a try
i found the results really profound i've
not carnivore now
been trying to reintroduce things and
see if they work for me and i'm still
kind of enough in the phase of trying
what really works um but i have a
greatly increased function
so that was question one question two uh
the trees
and uh what do we do and how should we
design our so those trees are
really beautiful but i have found
beautiful trees
all over the world and so i think a lot
of times people
don't see what's around them because
it's not sailing in their landscape
because they don't have the physical
skills
or awarenesses that would make them
you know very often on my videos oh if i
had trees like that
i would i would do that too it's
actually more the opposite
if they did what i did then they would
find the trees like that in there
obviously if you live in the middle of
the sahara desert or the arctic that's
not true
um but in most major cities there are
some beautiful trees in
the area that has lots of trees you can
start
um there there is stuff out there um
our environments have been designed to
make it easy for us to move around
um and that's uh that's okay for certain
purposes
it's also taken us taken us away from
exposure to things
the bodies need development is big
influence on me
talks about flat ground as a cage you're
constantly missing these nourishments
of uneven textures under our feet
the nourishment of hanging from things
and to climb
things so uh i
i like to go to the zoo and look at the
gibbon habitats and the
uh the primate habitats and i think that
like everyone should have a little bit
of primate habitat
in their house well maybe every office
should have a primate habitat
so human beings can go be primate we
forget
that we are but are and it actually is
uh i think it's i think it's
quite surprising how much becoming a
better monkey can contribute to becoming
a better human being
or eight for that matter
awesome thank you and i appreciate the
solidarity with the autoimmune condition
that's
i think it's important um there there
seem to be so many people with
autoimmune conditions
uh toiling away working in the world and
still able to
cope and manage so that's encouraging i
appreciate it thank you
we're at about 7 35 i want to be
respectful of your time ray but
did you have uh any more for a couple
more or
or should we yeah for a couple more
sure thank michael
we can oh no no
that's okay thank you oh sorry
you you you withdrew uh
and oh i think we're actually actually
one one question i wanted to ask
is so i uh you have children i have
children and
you talk a lot about uh being
a proponent of roughhousing and so
you know but i i i try to let my kids
roughhouse but i usually draw the line
at tears
uh you know what do you draw a line
between uh you know
the playing around rough and sort of
beating each other up
yeah so i mean our rule is that it has
to be consensual
i can i mean
sometimes my son will cry and he doesn't
want to give up the game
back in him
something that has been highlighted
particularly in my son recently
but something that reminds me of what
reiki played
so in our culture we have this idea that
play is
um whimsical and frivolous and we've got
play we imagine laughing and skipping
through the fields
children play is is actually much more
serious
some of it is that you'll see hear them
giggling and they'll be shrieking and
but um also see them really pushing
their edges
sometimes that that pushing their edge
and appreciation and dealing with the
other kids
emotions have to delegate those and
it's a huge aspect of what they're
learning so
just the other day um my son's five
years old
and there's a boy next door who's his
main playmate who's seven years old
uh the boy next door has been bodies
um i haven't pushed here to
to kind of get as formal with his
training in these things yet
um there's some couple out of background
and he's done some too
but he hasn't done as much
formal striking a round kick in the
solar plexus
and he walked away and he he was a
little bit
knocked out of him and tears in his eyes
um
i helped him regulate because i don't
want them to go to control but if he
chooses to go back into the game because
he feels like he's gonna
stop him
the big thing is that we have the role
that you can't punch anybody unless you
ask
you know you have to not be punching
anything
if it's in play when it's in
a mutual kind of growing experience then
it's welcome
you can push each other as hard as you
want but as soon as it becomes
punishing the other person
that's excellent i'm going to borrow
some of that so
i think we've reached the the end of our
questions and uh
thank you so much this has been amazing
i really appreciate your time and your
you've clearly just the depth of your
thought is
is apparent in in your answers so
thank you so much for being here today
thank you brett i really appreciate it
and thank you to everyone who
came in uh
the question thing and say uh
david wu there student of movement yeah
one of my friends in the air
and the group as well it's cool to see
this community coming together
yeah yeah sorry you're you're breaking
up there but uh
you know you were
yeah all right great well thank
thanks so much and thanks so much for
everyone being here uh
just to give a preview of events coming
up uh later this week friday
we've got uh layman pascal coming at 11
a.m eastern time there's a
live book reading about death at uh
at 5 00 pm eastern on friday 12 rules
for life
discussion book group on saturday at 10
a.m
eastern and uh awakening your inner
healer
these are organized by laureen at uh
at 4pm on on saturday and make sure you
check out our our calendar
our google calendar it's pinned in the
announcements channel
and again thanks everyone for being here
thank you tyler for
for recording and uh thanks ray for
for giving so much of your time and i
think everyone really enjoyed that
thank you very much thank you rafe
all right thanks ray and you're welcome
you're welcome to come back anytime
uh we we'd love to have you and we'd
love uh yeah and
you know check out our community as well
there's there's a lot of great
discussions going on
good i don't know how much time i have
but but it is
it is intriguing
thank you so much
oh he figured it out great well thanks
everyone that was another great